Guide to the Goddard Lieberson Papers
Yale University Music Library
- Writings by Goddard Lieberson, 1930-1975
  - Essays and speeches
    - Has there ever been an age... (Untitled) (Box 69, Folder 23a)
    - Hindemith (Box 69, Folder 24)
    - History of Columbia Records (Box 69, Folder 25)
    - Hot Semantics (Downbeat Magazine) (Box 69, Folder 26)
    - The Insider (High Fidelity), 1975-1977 (Box 69, Folder 27)
    - I've Got a Right to Sing the Blues (Album Notes: Eileen Farrell) (Box 69, Folder 28)
    - John Hammond Luncheon (Box 69, Folder 29)
    - Juilliard Commencement Speech, 1962 (Box 69, Folder 30)
    - The Limitation of Electronics (Box 69, Folder 31)
    - Lincoln College, 1969 (Box 69, Folder 32)
    - Mary Martin (Album Notes) (Box 69, Folder 33)
    - Mind Over Microphone (The Reporter), 1954-10-21 (Box 69, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 69, Folder 35)
    - MTA Dinner, 1973 (Box 69, Folder 36)
    - Music as an International Social Force (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - Music in U.S. (Untitled) (Box 70, Folder 2)
    - National Music Council Meeting, 1969 (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Nashville (Box 70, Folder 4)
    - Nashville Country Music (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - A New Show Every Day of the Year (Box 70, Folder 6)
    - New York Philharmonic, 1970 (Box 70, Folder 7)
    - New York Times Article (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Noel Coward in New York (Box 70, Folder 9)
    - The Non-Visual Theatre (Box 70, Folder 10)
    - Notes on Speeches Given (Box 70, Folder 11)
    - Of Manners for Microphones (High Fidelity), 1957 (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - On Musical Judgement (Box 70, Folder 13)
    - On the Town (Box 70, Folder 14)
    - One Man and His Time (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - One of my Favorite... (Untitled) (Box 70, Folder 16)
    - The Over-Trained Audience (The Reporter), 1955-01-27 (Box 70, Folder 17)
    - Playbill Article/Interview Drafts (Box 70, Folder 18)
    - Plays of Eugene O'Neil (Box 70, Folder 19)
    - A Plea for Listening, 1954 (Box 70, Folder 19a)
    - Pons-Kostelanetz Concert - Cincinnati Music Hall (Box 70, Folder 20)
    - The Psychopathology of Everyday Conducting (Box 70, Folder 21)
    - Radio Conference Speech, 1968 (Box 70, Folder 22)
    - Record Makers See Bright Future (Box 70, Folder 23)
    - Richard Tucker Memorial, 1975 (Box 70, Folder 24)
    - Scholastic Article (On Teenage Emotions) (Box 70, Folder 25)
    - Schwann Catalog, 1974 (Box 70, Folder 26)
    - September Song "Kurt and Lenya" (Box 70, Folder 27)
    - The Shape of Music (Box 70, Folder 28)
    - Short Remarks - Bernstein (Box 70, Folder 29)
    - Show Albums (Box 70, Folder 30)
    - Sigmund Freud (Grolier Club), 1956 (Box 70, Folder 31)
    - The Sounds of Love (The Reporter), 1954-06-22 (Box 70, Folder 32)
    - A Statement from Goddard Lieberson (RCA Dynagroove), 1963 (Box 70, Folder 33)
    - The Taste for Music (Box 70, Folder 34)
    - This is Broadway's Best (Box 70, Folder 35)
    - Three Men and an Orchestra (Box 70, Folder 36)
    - A Thurber Carnival (Box 70, Folder 37)
    - Tribute to John Hammond (Box 70, Folder 38)
    - Tribute to Robert Casadesus, 1973 (Box 70, Folder 39)
    - Trois Morceaux en Forme de Poire (Album Note: Satie) (Box 70, Folder 40)
    - The Ulcer Diet in Music (The Reporter) (Box 70, Folder 41)
    - Victor Babin Tribute (Box 70, Folder 42)
    - What Happened Since LP (Saturday Review), 1967-08-26 (Box 70, Folder 43)
  - Plays, poetry and books
    - Angels Unaware (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - The Bending Twig, 1948 (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - The Birdcage, 1958 (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - The Columbia Book of Musical Masterworks, 1947 (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - 1000 Musical Masterpieces (oversized) (Box 81, Folder 3)
      Publicity material for Columbia Book of Musical Masterworks
    - Fables (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - The Journals of Philabert Rye (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Mr. Jelly (Children's Book), 1939 (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - One Revolving Moon and the Liar (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - Play about Mandrake (Untitled) (Box 72, Folder 1)
    - Play about an orchestra (Untitled) (Box 72, Folder 2)
    - Poems (Box 72, Folder 3)
    - Poems (Box 72, Folder 4)
    - Story about Mr. Plato (Untitled) (Box 72, Folder 5)
    - Three for Bedroom C, 1947 (Box 73)
      Four novelization drafts, including corrections; Correspondence with list of corrections (one folder); Typewritten screenplay (by GL?).
    - Three for Bedroom C, 1947 (Box 74)
      Correspondence and reviews (2 folders); Typewritten screenplay by Corey Ford (2 copies); Typewritten screeplay by Milton Bren; Two photocopies of published novel; One copy of published novel.
  - Published articles and newspaper columns
    - 1930s (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - 1940s (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - 1950s (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - 1960s (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - 1970s (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - Undated (Box 75, Folder 6)
- Writings by others, 1930-1977
  This series contains both writings by others about Lieberson and writings by others that Lieberson held in his possession. The writings about Lieberson include an array of published reviews, profile pieces, and news articles relating to Columbia. The bulk of these writings dates from 1930-1977. This series is a valuable resource for tracing the public reception of Columbia recording projects, as well as Lieberson's own cultural legacy. Among the writings by others that Lieberson held in his possession are several published works and manuscripts of writings by friends or acquaintances of Lieberson's including a typescript version of Aldous Huxley's Brave New World, and the Complete Catalog of Works by Carlos Chávez.
  The "Published articles about Goddard Lieberson" subseries is organized chronologically. The "Other writings" subseries is organized alphabeticlly by title.
  - Published articles about Goddard Lieberson
    - 1930s (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - 1940s (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - 1950s (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - 1950s (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - 1950s (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - 1960s (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - 1960s (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - 1970s (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - 1970s (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - Post-1980 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - Undated (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - Other writings
    This series contains both writings by others about Lieberson and writings by others that Lieberson held in his possession. The writings about Lieberson include an array of published reviews, profile pieces, and news articles relating to Columbia. This series is a valuable resource for tracing the public reception of Columbia recording projects, as well as Lieberson's own cultural legacy. Among the writings by others that Lieberson held in his possession are several published works and copies of writings by Lieberson's friends and acquaintances, including a typescript version of Aldous Huxley's Brave New World and the Complete Catalog of Works by Carlos Chávez.
    - Complete Catalog of Works, Carlos Chávez (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - Published articles about Payola scandal (Box 76, Folder 7)
    - Julehelg [Christmas Weekend] - Gift from [Vera's] Aunts, 1952 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Huxley, Aldous - Brave New World (Box 77, Folder 2)
      Typescript of Musical Comedy
    - Kostelanetz, Richard - The Music of Today (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - Menotti, Gian Carlo - Making a Place for Modern Opera (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - Murray, Gilbert (Trans.) - Euripides (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - Ostrow, Stuart - Stages (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - Salamon, Pál - Provincialism (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - Stanton, Frank - Creative Playthings (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - "Touch & Thrash" (multiple authors) (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - Unattributed Writings (By Lieberson and/or Others) (Box 78, Folder 1)
- Scrapbooks and programs, 1950-1975
  - Programs, 1934-1977
    - Performances of Music/Drama by Lieberson (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - Lieberson Tribute Programs (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - CBS Event Programs (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 78, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 25th Anniversary Scrapbook Correspondence, 1964 (Box 78, Folder 7)
    - 25th Anniversary Scrapbook Correspondence, 1964 (Box 78, Folder 8)
    - 25th Anniversary Scrapbook, Volume 1, 1964 (Box 84)
      The first of two volumes celebrating Goddard Lieberson's twenty-five year anniversary at Columbia Records. Hardcover with reproduction of Al Hirschfeld's portrait of Lieberson on front cover. Inside pages contain upwards of 65 personalized notes of congratulations sent to Lieberson from famous artists and musicians with whom he worked during his first 25 years at the company. The first page of the volume includes a letter from William S. Paley, chairman of the board of directors at Columbia (and former president). Some photos of Lieberson are interspersed throughout the volume. Among the dozens of contributors to this volume, names include: Igor Stravinsky, Jacqueline Kennedy, Cole Porter, Richard Rodgers, Harold Prince, Truman Capote, and Rex Harrison. In addition to the letters contained in the volumes, the Goddard Lieberson Papers contain a small group of letters concerning the organization for these volumes and the twenty-fifth year anniversary, more generally.
    - 24th Anniversary Scrapbook, Volume 2, 1964 (Box 85)
      The second of two volumes celebrating Goddard Lieberson's twenty-five year anniversary at Columbia Records. Hardcover with reproduction of Al Hirschfeld's portrait of Lieberson on front cover. Inside pages contain upwards of 65 personalized notes of congratulations sent to Lieberson from famous artists and musicians with whom he worked during his first 25 years at the company. Some photos of Lieberson are interspersed throughout the volume. Among the dozens that contributed to this volume, names include: Eugene Ormandy, Andre Kostelanetz, Gertrude Hindemith (on behalf of Paul Hindemith after his death), Aaron Copland, André Previn, and one letter signed by all members of The New York Philharmonic. In addition to the letters contained in the volumes, the Goddard Lieberson Papers contain a small group of letters concerning the organization for these volumes and the twenty-fifth year anniversary, more generally.
    - Scrapbook with Elvis Presley cover (Box 86)
      Of unknown origin. Contains newspaper and magazine clippings, photos, headlines, and various advertisements. Contains a number of pictures of Lieberson, cut from new articles or profiles. This is not a scrapbook in the sense of a photo album, or something put together to commemorate an event. Rather, it is an assemblage of cut-outs pasted together with no particular narrative or goal. Given the range of jokes and innuendos that cover the pages, this scrapbook seems to have been put together in jest, though there is no signature, date, or epigraph to provide context.
- Personal documents and awards, 1957-1977
  - Awards and tributes
    - RIAA Appreciation Plaque, 1964-1966 (Box 78, Folder 9)
    - Maker of the Microphone Award, 1964 (Box 79, Folder 1)
      Contains paper documentation related to the Maker of the Mircrophone award from 1964. Award itself housed in Room 4 Cage.
    - Mexican Theater Critics Award, 1967 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - Grammy Award: Cabaret (Best Score from an Original Cast Album), 1967 (Box 83)
    - United Jewish Appeal of Greater New York Tribute, 1968 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - City of New York Certificate of Appreciation, 1968 (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - Richard Rogers Award, 1974 (Box 79, Folder 5)
    - Music Week and CBS Records UK Award, 1975 (Box 79, Folder 6)
    - Ruth Ellington Tribute, 1975 (Box 79, Folder 7)
    - Memorial Service, 1977 (Box 79, Folder 8)
    - City of Los Angeles Tribute, 1977 (Box 79, Folder 9)
    - Posthumous Donations Made in Honor of GL (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - A Film Tribute: Goddard Lieberson (Proposal), 1977 (Box 79, Folder 11)
    - Bright Eyes - Platinum (1M Sales) Record Award (oversized), 1980 (Box 81, Folder 1)
    - State of Tennessee Staff Colonel Commission (Box 79, Folder 12)
  - Honorary doctoral degrees
    - Temple University, 1957 (Box 79, Folder 13)
    - Cleveland Institute of Music, 1965 (Box 79, Folder 14)
    - Eastman School of Music, 1974 (Box 79, Folder 15)
    - Dartmouth College, 1975 (Box 79, Folder 16)
  - Personal documents, records and ephemera, 1922-1977
    - USA Naturalization Documents (Box 80, Folder 1)
    - Death Documents (Box 80, Folder 2)
    - Rosenberg Marriage Documents (Box 80, Folder 3)
    - CBS Job Documents and Finances (Box 80, Folder 4)
    - Personal Finances (Box 80, Folder 5)
    - Medical (Box 80, Folder 6)
    - Igor Stravinsky Will (Box 80, Folder 7)
    - Power of Attorney (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - Library of Congress GL Manuscripts Documents (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - School Records (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Teaching Notes and Contract Information (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Friends of GL Lists (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Name and address ink stamp (Box 87)
  - Bios
    - Lieberson Biographies, 1964-1977 (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous Biographical Information (Box 80, Folder 14)